Juan Ramón Jiménez Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Juan Ramón Jiménez Papers 1901-1954
MSS92429
Jiménez, Juan Ramón, 1881-1958
125 items
1 container
0.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Spanish poet. Letters, postcards, and poems written to Jiménez or his wife, Zenobia Camprubí de Jiménez, by such Spanish poets as Azorín, Rubén Darío, Antonio Machado, Alfonso Reyes, and Miguel de Unamuno.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Azorín, 1873-1967.; Camprubí, Zenobia, 1887-1956.; Darío, Rubén, 1867-1916.; Jiménez, Juan Ramón, 1881-1958.; Machado, Antonio, 1875-1939.; Reyes, Alfonso, 1889-1959.; Unamuno, Miguel de, 1864-1936.
Subjects
Poets, Spanish.; Spanish poetry.
Occupations
Poets.
Provenance
The papers of Juan Ramón Jiménez, Spanish poet, were given to the Library of Congress by Jiménez in 1949-1954. An addition was given by José María Longo in 1982.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Juan Ramón Jiménez are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Poet Juan Ramón Jiménez was born in 1881 in Moguer, Spain. He published his first book of poetry in 1900 with the help of Rubén Darío, the leader of the modernista poetry movement in Spain and influential mentor of Jiménez. During the Spanish Civil War, Jiménez moved first to Cuba and then to Puerto Rico where he spent most of the rest of his life. He was the recipient of the 1956 Nobel Prize in Literature. Jiménez died in San Juan, Puerto Rico in 1958.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Juan Ramón Jiménez (1881-1958) span the years 1901-1954. The papers are in Spanish and consist of letters, postcards, and poems written to Jiménez or his wife, Zenobia Camprubí de Jiménez, by such Spanish poets as Azorín, Rubén Darío, Antonio Machado, Alfonso Reyes, and Miguel de Unamuno. The largest number of poems and letters are by Rubén Darío.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and then by name of poet.
Container List
- Content lists (Box 1)
- Correspondence and poems (Box 1)
  - Azaña, Manuel, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Azorín (pseud.) [José Martínes Ruiz], 1910-1921 (Box 1)
  - Benavente y Martínez, Jacinto, undated (Box 1)
  - Cossío, José María de, 1919-1923 (Box 1)
  - Darío, Rubén (pseud.) [Félix Rubén García-Sarmiento] (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1901-1911 (Box 1)
    - Poems, undated (Box 1)
  - Falla, Manuel de, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Fitzmaurice-Kelly, James [Jaime], 1912 (Box 1)
  - Gómez de la Serna, Ramón, undated (Box 1)
  - Guerrero Ruiz, Juan, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Guillén, Jorge, 1923, 1933 (Box 1)
  - López-Picó, José María, 1915, undated (Box 1)
  - Machado y Ruiz, Antonio, circa 1903-1924, undated (Box 1)
  - Machado y Ruiz, Manuel, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Mallea, Eduardo, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Menéndez Pidal, Ramón, 1919, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Miró Ferrer, Gabriel, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  - Mistral, Gabriela (pseud.) [Lucila Godoy de Alcayaga], undated (Box 1)
  - Onís y Sánchez, Federico de, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Ors, Eugenio d’ [Xenius (pseud.)], 1915 (Box 1)
  - Ortega y Gasset, José, undated (Box 1)
  - Reyes, Alfonso, 1920, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Rueda y Santos, Salvador, undated (Box 1)
  - Sorolla y Bastida, Joaquín, 1909 (Box 1)
  - Unamuno y Jugo, Miguel de, 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Valle-Inclán, Ramón del, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Villaespesa, Francisco, undated (Box 1)
- Miscellany, 1949-1954 (Box 1)